It's now 3:40 in the morning
現在時間早上三點四十分
and I found a...
我發現一個...
It's not a secret~
也不算祕密拉~
The first time I came...
第一次來...
I found that all Taipei Stations were closed!!
發現臺北車站是全部關閉的!!
Even the toilets couldn't be used!!
連廁所都不能用!!
Then I finally saw a house He said at 7-11
然後有好不容易看到一家7-11
: We haven't opened yet
他說 : 我們還沒開始營業
and can't buy anything ,
也不能買東西
so we have to go outside to find the toilet and buy things
所以要去外面找廁所和買東西
. Now...
現在...
now we have to walk to...
現在要走到...
the M3 exit to wait for the shuttle bus...
M3出口這邊等接駁車...
and then we have to go out today. ....
然後今天要去....
Wuling!!
武嶺!!
Let's go...
要走...
Guguanyuanchu Pingfeng Mountain at the
石門山下古關原出屏風山
foot of Shimen Mountain.
期待今天的微探勘行程!!
Looking forward to today's micro exploration trip!!
石門山古關原出屏風山
The tribe is one of the fronts.
在日治時代，佐久間馬太征討太魯閣部落時其中一條戰線。
From the Shimen Mountain trailhead,
自石門山登山口起登
climb up the Baiyue Mountains with heavy equipment and the shortest distance.
重裝登上路程最短的百岳
From the top of the mountain, continue along
從山頭繼續沿著
the ridge extending eastward and cut all the way down to
向東延著稜脈一路下切至
the Tazkili Valley
塔次基里溪谷
to explore the little-known ancient Guanyuan and trace the history of
探訪那鮮為人知的古關原
more than a hundred years ago. The track of the Taroko War
追尋著百餘年前太魯閣戰爭的軌跡
turned around at the Pingfeng Mountain Trail and
並在屏風山山徑轉向
finally climbed to a drop of nearly 700 meters.
最後爬上將近700米的落差
From the Pingfeng New Trailhead to "going down the mountain",
自屏風新登山口「下山」
the entire trip accumulated a total of 1,300 meters of descent and a 700-meter climb.
整趟行程累積下降1,300米、爬升700米
The descent in one trip was more than the climb. Double the trip.
是一趟下降比爬升還要多上一倍的行程。
We now have to
我們現在要從...
go down from the east edge of Shimen Mountain!!
石門山東稜這邊下去!!
Sister Limei!!
麗美姊!!
Here!! Here!!
這裡!! 這裡!!
The path is not very obvious...
這個路徑沒有很明顯...
If you accidentally keep going down,
一不小心就一直往下走
you need to tie a piece of cloth here.
要綁一個布條在這邊
Otherwise, you will go down.
要不然就會走下去
Just after walking down the upper ridge...
剛剛從上稜線走下來之後...
If you are not careful, you will keep going down!!
如果不小心很順，會一直往下走!!
Go over there, that is wrong!! There is
往那邊去，那邊是不對的!!
a protruding point over there
在那邊一個凸出點
. The edge needs to be cut to the right!!
那邊就要往右邊切!!
Then there is a strip of cloth, go here!!
然後有布條，走到這邊!!
Next~ follow this path
接下來~順著這個路
...
這樣下去...
Sister Limei is tying the strip of cloth!!
麗美姐在綁布條!!
Thank you Sister Limei!!
謝謝麗美姊!!
Grass is taller than people !!
草比人高!!
On this side of the rocks...
在石塊這邊...
Next, we have to go into the woods to
接下來就要進樹林
lay up strips !!
布條!!
Red strips and yellow strips go up!!
紅布條跟黃布條這邊往上!!
Fight among the arrow bamboos and fallen trees!!
箭竹跟倒木之中奮戰!!
At the edge before reaching Guguanhara Although the offline cutting
在到達谷關原前的稜線下切
is not an extremely difficult place to reach
雖不是極難到達的地方
, you have to go through the arrow bamboo forest that is taller than a person
也須穿過比人高的箭竹林
and step over the fallen trees.
跨過倒木
Along the way, everyone's traveling skills and judgment are constantly tested
一路上也不斷考驗著大夥的行進技巧和判斷能力
(let's go!!) Okay~
(走囉!!)  好~
Now we are about to descend to Taziji. At the bottom of Lixi
現在快要下到塔次基里溪底
... After crossing the creek twice,
那...過兩次溪之後
you will arrive at today's camping spot!!
就會到達今天的紮營點!!
In fact, we are almost done climbing!!
其實也快爬完了!!
You can now hear the sound of the stream
現在可以聽到溪水聲
and the stream is close now!
現在溪水已經近了!!
Hurry down to Tazkili Creek. After
快下到塔次基里溪
we will almost arrive at today’s camp point
就快要到今天的紮營點
, and there are still about eight kilometers left in the total journey...
然後總歷程還剩下八公里左右...
Just out of Guguanyuan at the foot of Shimen Mountain...
就石門山下古關原出...
Pingfeng Mountain Trailhead
屏風山登山口
!! It’s starting to rain
哇!! 有點開始飄雨!!
a bit !! In front!!
溪在前面!!
You can already see the creek!!
已經可以看到溪了!!
Wow~
哇~
Now it’s contestant No. 2!!
現在是2號選手!!
Followed by contestant No. 3!!
緊接著是三號選手!!
Go Go Go!!
Go Go Go !!
We have to cross the creek later... So here
待會還要過溪... 所以就
we go...
所以就...
Let’s not put on shoes yet
先不穿鞋了
~ (It hurts)
阿~ (痛)
It’s a mistake not to bring slippers!!
沒有帶拖鞋真是失策!!
I just came up
剛才從...
from... the stream...
溪下面上來...
and now this is...
現在這邊就是...
the ancient Guguanyuan campground!!
古關原的營地!!
The stream is quite close and it’s convenient to get water. !!
溪邊蠻近的，取水方便!!
Let’s set up camp today
今天就在今天紮營
and take a look at our campsite today!!
來看一下我們今天的營地!!
Today’s...
今天...
sleeping place!!
睡的地方!!
The tent is set up and
帳篷搭好
next... we’ll move into the house!!
接下來...入厝!!
Now, we’ll set up camp on this side of Tashkili Creek.
現在，在塔次基里溪這邊紮營
It's the ancient Guanyuan...
這邊是古關原的...
The ruins of the ancient Guanyuan
古關原的遺址
. Why is the ancient Guanyuan called the ancient Guanyuan?
古關原為什麼叫古關原呢？
This was during the Japanese colonial period...
這是以前日治時代的時候 ...
The Japanese colonial government and
那日本殖民政府跟...
the Taroko people were competing for...
太魯閣族要爭奪...
some resources in the nearby mountainous areas!!
這附近山區的一些資源!!
So the ancient battlefield where the war started!!
所以發的戰爭的古戰場!!
It seemed like it was going to rain. ..Then
好像快下雨...
today...the time now is...
那今天就...現在時間是...
eat at 3:30
三點半
, then wash up and go to bed!!
吃一吃就洗洗睡!!
Check the mobile phone!!
刷手機!!
First like this!!
先這樣!!
Then get up at 7 o'clock tomorrow morning
然後明天早上七點
~
起來~
not get up!! It is to set off
不是起來!! 是七點出發
at 7 o'clock
那就先這樣囉~
That’s all for now~ After a night’s rest,
在經過一夜休整後
we packed up our equipment and headed back
收拾裝備踏上歸途
home at 7:20 in the morning.
早上七點二十
We set off at 7:00 this morning
我們今天早上七點出發的
and now we have just left...
那現在剛剛從...
Guguanyuan Campground.
古關原營地離開
Today... the mileage is about six kilometers
今天...里程大概走了六公里
. Back to...
就回到...
Pingfeng Mountain trailhead,
屏風山登山口
everyone is in front of us.
現在大家都在前面
There are still cloth strips along the way,
一路上還是有布條
so it's actually quite easy to walk
所以其實還算好走
. The sun comes out...
太陽出來了...
We pass through the pine needle forest that shines slightly under the sunlight,
穿過在陽光透漏下微微閃耀的松針樹林
then pick up the traditional path and return. At the end of these two days and one night in the civilized world
再接上傳統路徑，回到文明世界
, we are now 4.8 kilometers away from the trailhead
結束這兩天一夜的，秘境探險之旅
on our secret adventure tour.
我們現在離登山口還剩4.8公里
Today we came from...
我們今天從...
the camp of the ancient Guanyuan ancient battlefield
那個古關原古戰場的營地
and walked about 2K.
那邊過來，大概走了2K左右
Now I am taking the photo It's Sister Limei!!
現在掌鏡的是麗美姐!!
She thinks this place is very beautiful!! If you have to take a photo
她覺得這邊非常漂亮!! 一定要拍一下
, I will appear on camera and record the video.
那我就出鏡錄一下影
You can take a look at the surrounding...
大家可以看一下周圍的這個...
the sun is shining in the forest!! And...
陽光灑落森林!! 然後...
the gap is very beautiful. !!
間隙的樣子非常的漂亮!!
Iron suspension bridge
鐵線吊橋
Shimen Mountain...
石門山...
The last remaining
下古關原出屏風山
part of Xiaguguanyuan Chupingfeng Mountain
剩最後的...
... about one or two hundred meters...
大概一兩百公尺吧...
just back to the road!!
就回到馬路上!!
Today's journey
今天這趟旅程
I think...
我覺得...
except Next...
除了下...
the area on the east edge of Shimen Mountain...
石門山東稜那一塊...
it's a bit of a small exploration route.
有點微探勘路線
Some places require finding the way...
有些地方需要找路之外...
other places are pretty easy to walk.
其他地方都還算蠻好走
This time I went with Sister Limei and...
這一次跟麗美姊還有...
Sister Limei's friends. I thought it was a good experience
麗美姊的朋友、山友一起走
to walk with mountain friends
覺得是個不錯的體驗!!
!! Set up a tent to spend the night here in Guguanyuan!!
在古關原這邊搭帳棚過夜!!
Next to it is...
旁邊就是...
ㄜ... Liwu River!!
ㄜ...立霧溪!!
Tatsikili River!!
塔次基里溪!!
It is very convenient to get water
取水很方便
to sleep at night. When...
晚上睡覺的時候...
Listening to the sound of gurgling water, it's so good to fall asleep!!
聽著潺潺的水聲超好睡!!
That's about it for today~
今天就差不多先這樣囉~
Okay!! Goodbye~
好!! 掰掰~
Wow~ Sister Limei is done!!
哇~ 麗美姊走完了!!
What do you think?
什麼感想？
Finished!!
完登!!
Relaxed!! (Awesome!!)
輕輕鬆鬆!! (太棒了!!)
Thank you!! Everyone, let me eat with you!!
謝謝!! 各位陪我糜爛!!
Let’s try some fragrant pears~ We are so good that we
我們現在試吃香梨~ 我們真的很好
can even eat the skin!! It’s super delicious!! Really Yes!!
連皮都可以吃!! 超好吃的!! 真的!!
The boss said that one will be given to you!!
老闆說那一顆送你!!
Thank you, boss~
老闆謝謝喔~
No. 53 Sekihara!!
關原五十三號!!